<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://zer0sh0t.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://zer0sh0t.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-14T20:54:14+00:00</updated><id>https://zer0sh0t.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Reinforcement Learning-Based Model Matching in COBRA, a Slithering Snake Robot</title><link href="https://zer0sh0t.github.io/blog/2024/my-thesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reinforcement Learning-Based Model Matching in COBRA, a Slithering Snake Robot"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://zer0sh0t.github.io/blog/2024/my-thesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zer0sh0t.github.io/blog/2024/my-thesis/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2> <p>This work employs a reinforcement learning-based model identification method aimed at enhancing the accuracy of the dynamics for our snake robot, called COBRA. Leveraging gradient information and iterative optimization, the proposed approach refines the parameters of COBRA’s dynamical model such as coefficient of friction and actuator parameters using experimental and simulated data. Experimental validation on the hardware platform demonstrates the efficacy of the proposed approach, highlighting its potential to address sim-to-real gap in robot implementation.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <h2 id="simualtion-to-reality-gap">Simualtion-to-Reality Gap</h2> <p>Developing effective locomotion controllers for mobile robots is challenging, and while Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) offers promising solutions, it requires impractical amounts of training data for high-risk tasks like locomotion and manipulation. Although computer simulations provide a safe and efficient training environment, the resulting policies often fail to transfer effectively to real hardware due to the “Simulation-to-Reality Gap” (sim2real gap), caused by discrepancies such as differences in friction, joint dynamics, and sensor noise between simulated and real environments. These discrepancies impede the transition of control policies from simulation to real-world applications, resulting in suboptimal performance and limited generalization of robotic systems.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/sim2real_methods_new-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/sim2real_methods_new-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/sim2real_methods_new-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/sim2real_methods_new.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: Popular Solutions for Solving Sim2real Problem </div> <p>To tackle the challenges of the Simulation-to-Reality Gap, recent research has focused on several advanced strategies. These include employing more sophisticated system identification procedures to improve model accuracy, training policies on real robots while simultaneously enhancing simulator accuracy through domain adaptation, and developing robust control policies that can generalize across varied simulated environments through domain randomization. Although these methods have shown good transferability of learned policies from simulation to real robots, they typically require at least 1000 hours of training in the simulator and/or hundreds of rollouts on the real robot. The figure below highlights several state-of-the-art solutions addressing the sim2real problem across various robots.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/sota-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/sota-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/sota-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/sota.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 2: Shows successful transfer of an RL-based policy on 1) ANYmal robot 2) &amp; 6) Unitree A1 3) Hexapod 4) Cassie 5) Sirius 7) Mini Cheetah 8) 7-DoF Yumi Robot 9) &amp; 13) ANYmal C 10) ANYmal B 11) Digit humanoid 12) Soft Snake Robot </div> <hr/> <h2 id="simulators-and-physics-engines">Simulators and Physics Engines</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/sim_table-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/sim_table-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/sim_table-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/sim_table.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Table 1: Comparison of simulators </div> <p>Table 1 compares pros and cons of most widely used physics simulators for robotics applications. After considering all the options, I chose the Webots simulator as the ideal platform for bridging the sim2real gap in training reinforcement learning (RL) agents for the COBRA platform due to its robust integration capabilities with RL training and extensive resources for developing locomotion, manipulation, and navigation controllers. Webots offers a user-friendly interface and supports various programming languages like Python and C++, simplifying the implementation and integration of RL algorithms. Its diverse library of robot models, realistic physics simulations, and advanced visualization tools create an optimal environment for training RL-based locomotion policies. Additionally, Webots provides comprehensive tools and resources for developing controllers for various tasks essential to the COBRA platform’s functionality. Overall, Webots’ compatibility with RL training and its rich resources make it an excellent choice for addressing the sim2real gap in developing efficient controllers for the COBRA platform.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="motivation">Motivation</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/research_gap-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/research_gap-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/research_gap-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/research_gap.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 3: Highlights the shared aspects among the popular solutions to sim2real problem </div> <p>Significant progress has been made in simulation-to-reality transfer for locomotion tasks, but several research gaps remain. There is a strong motivation to develop a framework which:</p> <ol> <li>is data-efficient</li> <li>is learning-based</li> <li>is scalable</li> <li>is modular</li> <li>requires minimum rollouts on the real robot</li> <li>has standardized evaluation metrics for sim2real transfer</li> </ol> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here is a concise overview of the key ideas and findings from my thesis. Condensing a year's worth of brainstorming, programming, testing, reading, and writing into a single blog post is challenging, but I have done my best to capture the essence here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://zer0sh0t.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://zer0sh0t.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://zer0sh0t.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>